{
  "reference_number": "36",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "The Climate Change Commission can decide if it sees fit to increase the target - ie. be carbon negative by X% by 2050, or achieve\n carbon 0 before 2050."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "Disingenious question. What are you really asking here? Agriculture and its emmisions should not be given a free pass. Agriculture is\n\n our biggest emmitter and if we include them it forces us to find solutions. Pressure and stress are big motivators in getting the job\n done."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "This works best for brand NZ - clean green etc. If we can't do it with a population of only 4 million in a developed economy then either\n no one can or we are incompetent. We need to set an example, be innovative, find solutions that can be exported."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Unless its to accelerate the process. We need to shoot for the stars and worst case we reach the moon."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "If the case that this 3rd budget is to be watered down, there should be rigorous checks and measures."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Exceptional circumstances need to be clearly defined. A local natural disaster eg Christchurch earthquake should not be considered\n an exceptional circumstance. Perhaps we can put local exemptions in place in such a scenario but keep national targets unchanged.\n\n Also a global / national economic crash should not be an exeptional circumstance. (They're not really exceptional as they seem to\noccur every 10 years or so anyway and we are due for one soon it seems) In other words we should not allow the disfunction of our\n\neconomic system to dictate our emmision reduction targets. GDP, unemployment, inflation etc are not accurate measures of\neconomic and social health. We should not prioritise these false measures over life itself."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The government should be required to respond to recommendations from the CCCommisison within 1 to 3 months not 3 to 6."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Timeframe should be defined."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "UNEP - auditor or advisor."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Consider legislation that could trigger the Commision to take over decision making if the government fails to meet its targets, fails to\nset carbon budgets appropriately, fails to keep NZ's obligations under the ratified Paris Accord. Or a system where the Commission\n\ncan 'fine / sue' the government (or the even better the ruling party/ies) and monies used for appropriate carbon e reduction activities."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Prioritise society over the economy pls"
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Biggest adaptation needed is to foster and allow the building of a parallel economy that mitigates as much as possible the potential\n\nfor total collapse and chaos. Decentralised renewable energy grids. Business shifting to a social enterprise model (as opposed to\nprivate, shareholder) to keep things going - supply chains etc. Ensure food stability and security - localised vertical farms for eg.\n\nCommunity resilience and self-sufficiency. Decentralisation. Crypto. 4 day then 3 day work week to save resources. So much to do...."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "You have elected to withhold your personal details from publication."
    }
  ]
}
